<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         id="41978b89-ae3f-4719-9004-bbdb79e0dba1"
         title="Introduction">

  <Paragraph>
    The <Term type="package">idstore</Term> package provides a server and client for managing user accounts.
  </Paragraph>

  <FormalItem title="Features">
    <ListUnordered>
      <Item>
        Simple, centralized identity storage and password checking. Passwords are securely stored using PBKDF2.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Email-based password reset functionality with a minimalist web interface.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Full API access for all operations: Separate user-facing and administrator-facing APIs are exposed on different
        ports and are accessed using an efficient binary protocol over HTTP.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Full Java API for performing user and administrative operations.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Strong separation between administrators and users.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Fine-grained capability based security model for administrative operations; Safely write external services that
        can perform administrative operations while maintaining the principle of least privilege.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Command-line administrative shell.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Complete audit log; every operation that changes the state of the system is logged in an append-only log.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Fully instrumented with <LinkExternal target="https://opentelemetry.io/">OpenTelemetry</LinkExternal>.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        A small, easily auditable codebase with a heavy use of modularity for correctness.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        An extensive automated test suite with high coverage.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Platform independence. No platform-dependent code is included in any form, and installations can largely be
        carried between platforms without changes.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <LinkExternal target="https://www.osgi.org/">OSGi</LinkExternal>-ready
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <LinkExternal target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_Platform_Module_System">JPMS</LinkExternal>-ready
      </Item>
      <Item>
        Support for <LinkExternal target="https://www.io7m.com/software/canonmill">Canonmill</LinkExternal> keystores.
      </Item>
      <Item>
        ISC license.
      </Item>
    </ListUnordered>
  </FormalItem>

</Section>
