<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         id="e7b8d1c0-1329-4bcd-aabb-276d0219593b"
         title="Model">

  <Subsection title="Overview">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="package">idstore</Term> server is primarily intended to act as a single-source-of-truth for the
      identities of users within arbitrary sets of decoupled services. It acts as a secure store for login credentials
      for users, and is intended to relieve server application authors of the burden of having to constantly reimplement
      login processes, credential stores, password reset workflows, and other miscellanea related to authentication.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      This section of the documentation describes the internal <Term type="package">idstore</Term> model.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Users/Administrators"
              id="c75582e9-741d-417d-9b65-1106d65e79bb">
    <Subsection title="Separation">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="package">idstore</Term> package contains two types of user accounts:
        <Term type="term">users</Term>
        and <Term type="term">administrators</Term>. A <Term type="term">user</Term> is an unprivileged account that is
        permitted to log in to the server only via the <Link target="dae57724-5cd8-46b3-8650-1c3becce481e">user
        view</Link>, and/or the <Link target="01d8e9c6-54c0-4501-8f45-e6988e0cb673">user API</Link>. An
        <Term type="term">administrator</Term>
        is an account that is permitted to log in to the server only via the
        <Link target="f695a0a9-cec2-4db8-839d-e9eaaa8dace3">admin API</Link>, and is permitted to perform administrative
        actions (subject to
        <Link target="40fe0926-7d6e-41e3-8a3a-9776d6ac3a5d">permissions</Link>
        checks) such as creating user accounts, reading the
        <Link target="0610ec24-6507-4a19-9efe-f511c31ccc9a">audit log</Link>, etc.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Identifiers">
      <Paragraph>
        <Term type="term">User</Term>
        and <Term type="term">administrator</Term> accounts have immutable, unique identifiers represented by
        <LinkExternal target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4122">RFC 4122</LinkExternal>
        UUID values. Identifiers are not secret and may be freely shared between systems.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Names">
      <Paragraph>
        <Term type="term">User</Term>
        and <Term type="term">administrator</Term> accounts have names that are
        used for login operations. Names must match the regular expression
        <Term type="expression">\p{LC}[\p{LC}\p{N}_-]{0,255}</Term>. Names
        are case-insensitive <LinkFootnote
        target="c19fc056-ddcf-48bd-ab7d-f8773772c5e8"/>
        and must be unique within a given
        <Term type="package">idstore</Term> server, but can be changed at the
        user/administrator's discretion at any time.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Email Addresses">
      <Paragraph>
        <Term type="term">User</Term>
        and <Term type="term">administrator</Term> accounts must have at least one unique (within a given
        <Term type="package">idstore</Term>
        server) email address associated with them. Email addresses can be added and removed at any time, but it is not
        permitted for the number of addresses on an account to be less than one.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Permissions" id="634db1a2-1705-44ae-abac-8fa281b100f4">
      <Paragraph>
        Each <Term type="term">administrator</Term> account has a set of
        <Link target="40fe0926-7d6e-41e3-8a3a-9776d6ac3a5d">permissions</Link>
        associated with it. When the administrator account attempts to perform an operation on the server, the account's
        permissions are checked to see if it has all the permissions required to perform the action.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        An <Term type="term">administrator</Term> account holding the
        <Term type="constant">ADMIN_WRITE_PERMISSIONS</Term>
        permission may <Term type="term">grant</Term> any permissions it holds to another
        <Term type="term">administrator</Term>
        account. Similarly, An <Term type="term">administrator</Term> account holding the
        <Term type="constant">ADMIN_WRITE_PERMISSIONS</Term>
        permission may <Term type="term">revoke</Term> any permissions it holds from another <Term type="term">
        administrator
      </Term> account.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Initial Administrator"
                id="f3d98730-c3b1-4da7-8f82-94aa9c99d473">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="term">initial administrator</Term> is a designated adminstrator account that always has all of
        the available <Link target="40fe0926-7d6e-41e3-8a3a-9776d6ac3a5d">permissions</Link>. For security reasons, this
        account should have an extremely strong password, and should only be used to perform the necessary initial
        configuration of the server; it is analogous to the UNIX <Term type="expression">root</Term> account.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Permissions"
              id="40fe0926-7d6e-41e3-8a3a-9776d6ac3a5d">
    <Paragraph>
      The following administrator permissions are available:
    </Paragraph>
    <FormalItem title="Permissions">
      <Table type="genericTable">
        <Columns>
          <Column>Permission</Column>
          <Column>Description</Column>
        </Columns>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_DELETE</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to delete administrator accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_CREATE</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to create new administrator accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_BAN</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to ban users.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_BAN</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to ban administrators.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_CREDENTIALS</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify the credentials of administrators.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_CREDENTIALS_SELF</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify its own credentials.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_EMAIL</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify the email addresses of administrators.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_EMAIL_SELF</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify its own email addresses.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_PERMISSIONS</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify the permissions of administrators.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_WRITE_PERMISSIONS_SELF</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify its own permissions.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>ADMIN_READ</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to read the accounts of administrators.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>AUDIT_READ</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to read the audit log.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_DELETE</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to delete user accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_CREATE</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to create new user accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_WRITE_CREDENTIALS</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify the credentials of existing user accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_WRITE_EMAIL</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to modify the email addresses existing user accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>USER_READ</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to read existing user accounts.</Cell>
        </Row>
        <Row>
          <Cell>MAIL_TEST</Cell>
          <Cell>The bearer of this permission is permitted to send test emails.</Cell>
        </Row>
      </Table>
    </FormalItem>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Audit Log"
              id="0610ec24-6507-4a19-9efe-f511c31ccc9a">
    <Paragraph>
      The server maintains an append-only <Term type="term">audit log</Term> consisting of a series of
      <Term type="term">audit events</Term>. An <Term type="term">audit event</Term> has an integer
      <Term type="term">id</Term>, an <Term type="term">owner</Term> (represented by an account UUID),
      a <Term type="term">timestamp</Term>, a <Term type="term">type</Term>, and a
      <Term type="term">message</Term>.
    </Paragraph>
    <FormalItem title="Audit Log">
      <Image source="audit.png"
             width="640"
             height="517">Audit log.
      </Image>
    </FormalItem>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="User View"
              id="dae57724-5cd8-46b3-8650-1c3becce481e">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="term">user view</Term> is the web interface exposed to users. It offers the ability for users to
      see their own account information, and also to handle the email-based password reset workflow.
    </Paragraph>
    <FormalItem title="Web Interface">
      <Image source="web.png"
             width="640"
             height="503">Web interface.
      </Image>
    </FormalItem>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="User API"
              id="01d8e9c6-54c0-4501-8f45-e6988e0cb673">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="term">user API</Term> is the interface exposed to user clients. It exposes
      a <LinkExternal target="https://www.io7m.com/software/cedarbridge">Cedarbridge</LinkExternal>-based API over HTTP,
      using the included
      <Link target="5242f097-2f68-4f19-8293-7a7ce68a8b7e">schema</Link>.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The user API is largely intended to be used by other servers that want to use an
      <Term type="package">idstore</Term>
      server to handle authentication.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Admin API"
              id="f695a0a9-cec2-4db8-839d-e9eaaa8dace3">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="term">admin API</Term> is the interface exposed to administrators. Like the
      <Link target="01d8e9c6-54c0-4501-8f45-e6988e0cb673">user API</Link>, it exposes a Cedarbridge-based API over HTTP,
      using the included
      <Link target="894a0f26-590b-4d08-b445-1b687c87b583">schema</Link>. It is the service used by the
      included <Link target="80d0af5f-505b-4dee-b733-296a6f3970a4">admin shell</Link>, and by projects such
      as <LinkExternal target="https://www.github.com/io7m-com/idstore_gui">idstore_gui</LinkExternal>.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Mail" id="0ad1864f-7eac-4700-ae06-66a4f0a3b97f">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        There are a number of situations where the <Term type="package">idstore</Term> server uses an external MTA.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Password Reset" id="f3535c44-486a-4236-ae34-765c7f763fe9">
      <Paragraph>
        If a user forgets their password, they can request a password reset <Term type="term">token</Term>. The server
        will generate a strong random <Term type="term">token</Term> <Term type="expression">t</Term> with a
        configurable expiration date. For each email address <Term type="expression">e</Term> associated
        with the user's account, the server will email <Term type="expression">t</Term> to
        <Term type="expression">e</Term>. The user can retrieve <Term type="expression">t</Term>
        from one of their email accounts and recite <Term type="expression">t</Term> back to the server to
        have their password reset.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Email Additions">
      <Paragraph>
        If a user wants to add a new email address <Term type="expression">f</Term> to their account,
        they can request email addition <Term type="term">tokens</Term>. The server
        will generate a pair of strong random <Term type="term">tokens</Term> <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term>
        and <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term>, each with a configurable expiration date.
        For each email account <Term type="expression">e</Term> associated
        with the user's account, the server will email <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term> to
        <Term type="expression">e</Term>. The server will email <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term>
        to <Term type="expression">f</Term>. Assuming the user really does have access to
        <Term type="expression">f</Term>, they can read the resulting email and recite
        <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term> back to the
        <Term type="package">idstore</Term> server to have the new address added to their account.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        In the event that the user's account is compromised, and a hostile party is attempting to add a new
        email address to the user's account, the user can recite <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term> back
        to the server from any of their other email accounts in order to deny the address addition. This potentially
        alerts users to the fact that their account has been compromised, and allows them to mitigate the damage
        if they act fast enough.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Email Removals">
      <Paragraph>
        If a user wants to remove an existing email address <Term type="expression">f</Term> from their account,
        they can request email removal <Term type="term">tokens</Term>. The server
        will generate a pair of strong random <Term type="term">tokens</Term> <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term>
        and <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term>, each with a configurable expiration date.
        For each email account <Term type="expression">e</Term> associated
        with the user's account (where <Term type="expression">e != f</Term>),
        the server will email <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term> to
        <Term type="expression">e</Term>. The server will email <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term>
        to <Term type="expression">f</Term>. Assuming the user really does have access to
        <Term type="expression">f</Term>, they can read the resulting email and recite
        <Term type="expression">tpermit</Term> back to the
        <Term type="package">idstore</Term> server to have the address removed from their account.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        In the event that the user's account is compromised, and a hostile party is attempting to remove the
        user's existing email address from the compromised account, the user can recite
        <Term type="expression">tdeny</Term> back
        to the server from any of their other email accounts in order to deny the address removal. This
        potentially alerts users to the fact that their account has been compromised, and allows them to mitigate
        the damage if they act fast enough.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        If the user no longer has access to <Term type="expression">f</Term>, they cannot remove it. In this
        case, an administrator will need to remove the address manually.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Maintenance Mode" id="8f3aa434-a254-49b4-9ea4-68c8f6ecfdd9">
    <Paragraph>
      When performing essential maintenance such as a database upgrade, the server can be placed
      into <Term type="term">maintenance</Term> mode. In this mode, all requests made to the
      <Link target="01d8e9c6-54c0-4501-8f45-e6988e0cb673">user API</Link> or
      <Link target="dae57724-5cd8-46b3-8650-1c3becce481e">user view</Link> will return a
      <Term type="constant">503</Term> HTTP status code and a configurable message.
    </Paragraph>
    <FormalItem title="Maintenance Mode">
      <Image source="maintenance.png"
             width="640"
             height="451">Maintenance mode.
      </Image>
    </FormalItem>
    <Paragraph>
      Maintenance mode is not a persistent setting; if the server is restarted, it will start up
      in the normal non-maintenance mode.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Footnote id="c19fc056-ddcf-48bd-ab7d-f8773772c5e8">
    Names are case-insensitive in order to make it slightly more difficult for
    a hostile user to impersonate another by picking a name that only varies
    with case.
  </Footnote>

</Section>
